Finding Aid for Michigan Interscholastic Forensic Association records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Interscholastic Forensic Association records 1897-2006, 1974-2002
Michigan Interscholastic Forensic Association
53 linear feet
0677 Bh 2
The Michigan Interscholastic Forensic Association (MIFA) was founded in 1933 to administer high school forensics contests throughout the state of Michigan. The policies and activities of MIFA are determined by a Forensic Council, and records pertaining to the council are included as a subseries in this collection. There are four main speech activities that are sponsored by MIFA: debate, individual events, drama/theatre, and legislative debate. Materials pertaining to specific components of these general activities form the bulk of the collection. Overall, the records largely span the years 1974-2004, although older items are scattered throughout the collection, including materials from two legacy organizations.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were first received in 2005 (Donor no. 9624 ) through MIFA and Executive Director Jon Fitzgerald.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open without restriction.
The Michigan Interscholastic Forensic Association (MIFA) was founded in March, 1933, as the Michigan High School Forensic Association (MHSFA). The new association consolidated three organizations that had promoted public speaking in Michigan during the previous thirty-seven years: the Michigan High School Oratorical Association, which began in 1896 as part of the Michigan Education Association, but came under sponsorship of the Michigan State Department of Agriculture in 1914; the Extempore Speaking Association of Michigan High Schools, organized in 1926 by Professor Carroll P. Lahman in Kalamazoo; and the Michigan High School Debating League, started in 1916 by the Extension Service of the University of Michigan, and is the most direct predecessor of the MHSFA. Materials pertaining to two of these legacy organizations form part of the collection. The MHSFA remained under the direction of the University of Michigan Extension Division until December 1948, when the university transferred it to the Bureau of School Services (BSS). Currently functioning as an independent body, MIFA administers most of the extracurricular speech activities for high school students in Michigan.
The goals of the MHSFA were to create "a sound, consistent program of speech training for the high schools in the state" and to be receptive to the needs and advice of high school officials throughout Michigan (Administration Series, Box 14, Irwin history, p.5). The association established a Forensic Council of school officials and administrators to establish policy and oversee its programs. Initially, the Forensic Council was composed of six members, with two representatives each from The Michigan Association of Teachers of Speech, The Michigan Conference of City Superintendents, and the Michigan Secondary School Association (Administration Series, Box 14, Grosser history). In 1944, two additional members representing the coaches in Michigan were added to the Forensic Council. Currently, the council is composed of 14 members. In addition to the Forensic Council, a State Manager position was instituted to provide oversight for the more routine business of the association. This position was typically filled by faculty of the Department of Speech at the University of Michigan. Presently, the State Manager position has been changed to that of Executive Director, who is an ex officio member of the Forensic Council.
The functions of MIFA are most closely identified with debate, historically the organization's most popular and recognizable event. In the first few years, debates were conducted as single elimination contests, however, a point system was implemented beginning in the early 1920s to ensure several preliminary debates for each participating team. Three-member teams were initially used in debate, but this arrangement underwent a permanent change to two-person teams in 1942. Another significant aspect of the early years of debate was the recognition of participants. Beginning in 1923, the Detroit Free Press provided prestigious awards to students who qualified for the State Championship Debates. The Free Press also gave plaques to schools with distinguished debate records and awarded individual merit certificates. In addition to team contests, individual debaters competed for the Detroit Free Press Debate Scholarship Contest starting in 1948. This was later named the John S. Knight Scholarship Contest for the Pulitzer Prize winning publisher of the Free Press. The support of the Detroit Free Press for MIFA-sponsored debate activities still continues today. Among other notable changes in debate through the years was the creation of a novice team state tournament in 1970. The objective was to provide a competitive format for high school students who lacked debate experience. The MIFA also adopted a judge certification process for debate judges in 1978. The three-part process included a written examination, completion of a ballot for a taped debate, and attendance at an analysis session on the current debate topic. The certification of judges was the first program of its kind in the country.
In the 1930s, the MHSFA sponsored four contests: Debate, Extempore Speaking, Declamation and Oratory, but as early as April, 1935, there were discussions in the Forensic Council about adding additional contests. During the 1950s, the council approved several new contests, including Humorous Reading, Interpretative Reading, Discussion, Dramatic Monologue, Dramatic Dialogue, Narrative Reading, Lyric Poetry Reading, and Radio News Commentary. The first state forensic tournament was held in 1965 at the University of Michigan as a double elimination tournament with champions crowned in five events: original oratory, extempore speaking, declamation, humorous reading, and interpretive reading. These forensic tournaments are grouped under the activity currently known as individual events. State champions are crowned in fourteen events, two of which rotate each year and are specifically designed for ninth and tenth grade students. Prior to these state tournaments, students only competed in local, district, and regional tournaments. The Detroit News awarded Webster's Collegiate Dictionaries to the district winners in these forensic contests, while the schools of regional champions received a wall banner from the University of Michigan Extension Service.
In an attempt to create a scholarship contest in individual events, essentially the equivalent to the John S. Knight contest in debate, the MIFA began a Sweepstakes tournament in the spring of 1968. This format allowed students to compete in five separate forensic events. Although funding was never realized to make this a true scholarship event, the contests have continued as the annual Interpretation Pentathlon. In addition, an Original Interpretation tournament was begun in the 1995-1996 academic year. Middle Level contests for junior high or middle school students started in the 1973-1974 school year. Two such contests are held each year with students competing in one of eight events. Among other significant changes in individual events was an at-large process for participation in regional and state contests instituted in 1990-1991. In addition, a judge certification procedure, similar to that utilized in debate, was implemented in the 1990s. Finally, the district, regional, and state individual events tournaments went to a two class system (Class A and Class B/C/D) to provide more equal competition beginning with the 1996-1997 year. Overall school sweepstakes champions in three classes, based on a points formula of participants, have been determined at the State Individual Events Tournaments. This sweepstakes competition should not be confused with the contest by the same name mentioned earlier.
In 1951, a group-based activity termed Discussion was started. Topics for these Discussion programs were often related to the current debate topics. The intent of Discussion was to provide a non-competitive environment of reflective thinking to determine a possible solution to the stated topic. In 1967, the association conducted its first Student Congress in Lansing where students simulate the activities of the legislative branch of our Federal Government. Students are selected for Student Congress based upon points earned the previous spring in Discussion festivals. The Detroit News provided financial and personnel support of the Student Congress for a number of years. Recently, Student Congress and Discussion have been renamed Legislative Debate. Among the changes that have taken place since the inception of Student Congress are the inclusion of a press corps and the establishment of a representative executive branch. The MIFA continues to utilize the facilities of the Michigan State Capitol for the Student Congress activity.
The last of the four main activities administered by MIFA, theatre, made its debut in 1969. In that year, Robert Koger, director of drama at St. John's High School, organized a regional theatre festival. This concept took hold and the MIFA held its first multi-level competition during the 1970-1971 school year. Previously known as one-act plays or drama contests, these events are technically festivals, with selected participants receiving excellent or superior recognition. Among the notable modifications to the theatre festivals over the years was the creation of the Teachers of the Year awards in 1975-1976 to recognize the outstanding achievements of one or two high school drama teachers. Two of the top plays in each state festival were selected to represent MIFA at the annual Michigan Youth Arts Festivals.
The Forensic Council approved a shift of administrative responsibilities during the early 1970s. In, 1969, while finding a replacement for State Manager James Irwin, the council discussed "taking a greater role in formulating policies, with the State Manager being the administrator of the program and responsible to the Council." The MHSFA was renamed the Michigan Interscholastic Forensic Association on June 13, 1975. The change was authorized by the Forensic Council in order to acknowledge "the diverse composition of the organization" and its programs (Box 1, folder "June 13, 1975," Forensic Council minutes). In 1985, a reorganization of the School of Education eliminated the BSS. The MIFA then joined its replacement, the Bureau of Accreditation and School Improvement Studies (BASIS). During the 1988-1989 academic year, the MIFA assumed full responsibility for its own finances. When the BASIS closed on June 30, 1992, the School of Education allowed the MIFA to retain its office space. However, in August 1996, the MIFA's university accreditation ended, and its office was transferred to the Stearns Building on North Campus. In 2002, the MIFA office left the university campus and moved to 2011 South State Street, where it remains as of 2008.
In the 1990s, the association responded to shifting trends in education and technology. In 1993, the council decided to permit students of home schooling to participate in MIFA contests provided they were sponsored by the activity director of a participating school. In 1996, the council discussed guidelines for students' use of the internet as a source of evidence. In 1996 and 1999, the council discussed the question of "offensive material" in theatre productions and whether audiences should be given disclaimers ahead of time. The council eventually recognized audience members' option to leave if they objected to a production's content.
____________________________
Sources:
Secord, Arthur E. and Thomas, Ruth H. Speech in the Extracurriculum Program. NASSP Bulletin (November, 1945) 29:116-124. Available at http://bul.sagepub.com
Grosser, L., "A Study of the History, Administration, and Techniques of the Michigan High School Forensic Association Contests," 1948 (Administration Series, Box 14).
Irwin, James. R., "The Michigan High School Forensic Association," Forensic News, May-June 1968-1969. (Administration Series, Box 14).
For current information about MIFA programs and contests, consult the MIFA website available as of April, 2005, at the following URL: http://www.themifa.org.
The records of the Michigan Interscholastic Forensic Association (MIFA) document the organization's growth from the 1930s to the 2000s, but most of its records concern the years after 1964, and in particular, the period from 1974 to 2002. The records are divided into eight: Administration, Publications, Photographs, Scrapbooks, Multimedia, Activities, Michigan High School Oratorical Association,, and Files of Jon Fitzgerald, Executive Director of MIFA.. The Forensic Council Minutes (in the Administration Series) and the Publications Series are the most useful parts of the collection for the researcher to gain an understanding of MIFA. The Activities, Photographs, and Multimedia series provide the best accounts of student participation.
Subjects:
Michigan High School Forensic Association.; Forensic oratory.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Administration 1934-2006
  The Administration series details the interactions between the governing heads of MIFA (the Forensic Council and State Manager), their members, and their sponsoring institution. The series also documents special initiatives undertaken to assist in MIFA's administration. The series is divided into four subseries: Forensic Council, Mailings, Standing Committees, and Topical Files. The Forensic Council contains the agendas, minutes, reports, and supporting documents of the Council's meetings and is, by far, the most comprehensive and orderly subseries. The files are arranged chronologically in this subseries. The Standing Committees subseries is composed of records pertaining to meetings of the debate, individual events, drama/theatre, and discussion/student congress committees. There are also a few files of the Middle Level individual events committee. These files are typically arranged chronologically by school year and are not complete. Many of the items in these files will also be found in the Forensic Council subseries, but it might be easier to first check the committee files to locate information concerning one of the MIFA activities. The subseries Mailings, 1967-2004, is arranged chronologically and contains materials mailed to coaches and participating schools. While a portion of these records can also be found in the Forensic Council series, these documents have been retained in this arrangement as full examples of the volume of material received by member schools during their participation in MIFA activities. The last subseries in this portion of the collection is of Topical Files, which arranges information alphabetically by topic rather than chronologically.
  - Forensic Council 1934-2006
    - 1934-1947 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1966 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - May 17, 1974 (Box 1)
    - June 7, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Bound Materials September 1, 1974-June 13, 1975 (Box 1)
    - October 11, 1974 (Box 1)
    - October 25, 1974 (Box 1)
    - December 13, 1974 (Box 1)
    - January 10, 1975 (Box 1)
    - March 3, 1975 (Box 1)
    - April 18, 1975 (Box 1)
    - May 17, 1975 (Box 1)
    - June 13, 1975 (Box 1)
    - September 6, 1975 (Box 1)
    - October 3, 1975 (Box 1)
    - December 12, 1975 (Box 1)
    - January 9, 1976 (Box 1)
    - March 8, 1976 (Box 1)
    - May 3, 1976 (Box 1)
    - June 12, 1976 (Box 1)
    - October 1, 1976 (Box 1)
    - December 10, 1976 (Box 1)
    - January 7, 1977 (Box 1)
    - March 1, 1977 (Box 1)
    - May 20, 1977 (Box 1)
    - June 9, 1977 (Box 1)
    - October 7, 1977 (Box 2)
    - December 9, 1977 (Box 2)
    - January 6, 1978 (Box 2)
    - March 6, 1978 (Box 2)
    - May 1, 1978 (Box 2)
    - May 19, 1978 (Box 2)
    - June 15, 1978 (Box 2)
    - October 6, 1978 (Box 2)
    - December 8, 1978 (Box 2)
    - January 19, 1979 (Box 2)
    - March 12, 1979 (Box 2)
    - April 30, 1979 (Box 2)
    - May 18, 1979 (Box 2)
    - June 15, 1979 (Box 2)
    - October 12, 1979, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - December 7, 1979 (Box 2)
    - January 18, 1980 (Box 2)
    - March 10, 1980 (Box 2)
    - April 28, 1980 (Box 2)
    - May 16, 1980 (Box 2)
    - June 13, 1980 (Box 2)
    - June 25, 1980 (Box 2)
    - October 3, 1980 (Box 2)
    - December 5, 1980 (Box 2)
    - January 1, 1981 (Box 2)
    - March 16, 1981 (Box 3)
    - April 27, 1981 (Box 3)
    - May 15, 1981 (Box 3)
    - June 5, 1981 (Box 3)
    - October 2, 1981 (Box 3)
    - December 11, 1981 (Box 3)
    - January 25, 1982 (Box 3)
    - March 8, 1982 (Box 3)
    - May 3, 1982, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - May 17, 1982 (Box 3)
    - June 7, 1982 (Box 3)
    - October 8, 1982 (Box 3)
    - November 22, 1982 (Box 3)
    - January 24, 1983 (Box 3)
    - March 7, 1983, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - May 2, 1983 (Box 3)
    - May 16, 1983 (Box 3)
    - June 13, 1983 (Box 3)
    - October 7, 1983, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - November 21, 1983 (Box 3)
    - January 23, 1984 (Box 3)
    - March 5, 1984 (Box 4)
    - April 30, 1984 (Box 4)
    - May 14, 1984 (Box 4)
    - June 4, 1984 (Box 4)
    - October 5, 1984, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - December 7, 1984 (Box 4)
    - January 21, 1985 (Box 4)
    - March 11, 1985, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - April 26, 1985 (Box 4)
    - May 22, 1985 (Box 4)
    - June 17, 1985 (Box 4)
    - October 11, 1985, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - December 6, 1985 (Box 4)
    - January 20, 1986 (Box 4)
    - March 3, 1986 (Box 4)
    - April 25, 1986 (Box 4)
    - June 10, 1986 (Box 4)
    - October 3, 1986, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - December 12, 1986 (Box 4)
    - January 27, 1987 (Box 5)
    - March 9, 1987 (Box 5)
    - April 24, 1987 (Box 5)
    - June 8, 1987 (Box 5)
    - October 2, 1987 (Box 5)
    - December 11, 1987 (Box 5)
    - December 11, 1987 (Incorporation) (Box 5)
    - January 26, 1988 (Box 5)
    - March 7, 1988 (Box 5)
    - April 29, 1988 (Box 5)
    - June 3, 1988 (Box 5)
    - June 17, 1988 (Box 5)
    - September 30, 1988 (Box 5)
    - December 9, 1988 (Box 5)
    - January 23, 1989 (Box 5)
    - March 6, 1989 (Box 5)
    - May 1, 1989 (Box 5)
    - June 2, 1989 (Box 5)
    - October 6, 1989 (Box 5)
    - December 8, 1989 (Box 5)
    - January 22, 1990 (Box 5)
    - March 5, 1990 (Box 5)
    - June 1, 1990 (Box 5)
    - July 18, 1990 (Box 5)
    - October 5, 1990 (Box 5)
    - December 7, 1990 (Box 5)
    - January 21, 1991 (Box 5)
    - March 4, 1991 (Box 5)
    - April 29, 1991 (Box 5)
    - May 31, 1991 (Box 5)
    - October 4, 1991 (Box 6)
    - December 6, 1991 (Box 6)
    - January 20, 1992 (Box 6)
    - March 2, 1992, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - May 29, 1992, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - August 20, 1992 (Box 6)
    - October 2, 1992, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - January 19, 1993 (Box 6)
    - March 15, 1993 (Box 6)
    - May 25, 1993 (Box 6)
    - August 17-18, 1993 (Box 6)
    - October 1, 1993, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - January 26, 1994 (Box 6)
    - March 14, 1994 (Box 6)
    - May 25, 1994 (Box 6)
    - August 16-17, 1994 (Box 6)
    - October 7, 1994 (Box 6)
    - January 25, 1995 (Box 6)
    - March 13, 1995 (Box 6)
    - May 23, 1995 (Box 6)
    - August 14-15, 1995 (Box 6)
    - October 6, 1995 (Box 6)
    - December 12, 1995 (Box 6)
    - January 24, 1996 (Box 6)
    - March 11, 1996 (Box 6)
    - May 21, 1996 (Box 7)
    - August 12-13, 1996 (Box 7)
    - October 4, 1996 (Box 7)
    - January 22, 1997 (Box 7)
    - March 12, 1997 (Box 7)
    - May 22, 1997 (Box 7)
    - June 16, 1997 (Box 7)
    - July 14, 1997 (Restated Articles and Bylaws of the Corporation) (Box 7)
    - August 11-12, 1997 (Box 7)
    - October 3, 1997 (Box 7)
    - January 21, 1998 (Box 7)
    - March 11, 1998 (Box 7)
    - June 18, 1998 (Box 7)
    - July 14, 1998 (Box 7)
    - August 11-12, 1998 (Box 7)
    - October 2, 1998 (Box 7)
    - January 20, 1999 (Box 7)
    - March 10, 1999 (Box 7)
    - June 22, 1999 (Box 7)
    - August 9-10, 1999, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - October 1, 1999, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - January 19, 2000 (Box 8)
    - March 8, 2000, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - May 4, 2000 (Box 8)
    - June 20, 2000 (Box 8)
    - August 7-8, 2000 (Box 8)
    - October 6, 2000 (Box 8)
    - January 17, 2001 (Box 8)
    - March 7, 2001 (Box 8)
    - June 19, 2001, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - August 6-7, 2001 (Box 8)
    - October 5, 2001, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - January 16, 2002, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - March 6, 2002 (Box 8)
    - June 18, 2002, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - August 3-5, 2002 (Box 8)
    - October 4, 2002 (Box 8)
    - January 16, 2003 (Box 9)
    - March 6, 2003 (Box 9)
    - June 17, 2003 (Box 9)
    - August 4-5, 2003 (Box 9)
    - October 3, 2003, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - January 19, 2004 (Box 9)
    - March 4, 2004 (Box 9)
    - June 15, 2004 (Box 9)
    - August 2-3, 2004 (Box 9)
    - October 4, 2004 (Box 9)
    - January 17, 2005 (Box 9)
    - March 8, 2005 (Box 9)
    - June 14, 2005 (Box 9)
    - August 1-2, 2005 (Box 9)
    - September 30, 2005, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - January 16, 2006 (Box 9)
    - March 8, 2006 (Box 9)
    - June 19, 2006 (Box 9)
    - July 31-August 1, 2006, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Standing Committees
    - Debate 1979-2003
      - 1979-1980 (Box 10)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 10)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 10)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 10)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 10)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 10)
      - 1994-1995 (Box 10)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 10)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 10)
      - 2000-2001 (Box 10)
      - 2002-2003 (Box 10)
      - various years (Box 10)
    - Discussion/Student Congress 2002-2006
      - May 25, 1976 (Box 10)
      - April 25, 1977 (Box 10)
      - 1977-1978 (Box 10)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 10)
      - 1979-1980 (Box 10)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 10)
      - March 30, 1981 (Box 10)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 10)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 10)
    - Drama/Theatre 1983-2006
      - 1983-1984 (Box 10)
      - 1984-1985 (Box 10)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 10)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 10)
      - 1989-1992 (Box 10)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 10)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 10)
      - March 10, 1995 (Box 10)
      - 1995-1996 (Box 10)
      - 1996-1997 (Box 10)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 10)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 10)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 10)
      - 2000-2001 (Box 10)
      - 2001-2002 (Box 10)
      - 2002-2003 (Box 10)
      - 2003-2004 (Box 10)
      - 2004-2005 (Box 10)
      - 2005-2006 (Box 10)
    - Individual Events 1979-2003
      - 1979-1980 (Box 10)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 10)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 10)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 10)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 10)
      - 1984-1985 (Box 10)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 10)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 10)
      - 1994-1995 (Box 10)
      - 1995-1996 (Box 10)
      - 1996-1997 (Box 10)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 10)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 10)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 10)
      - 2000-2001 (Box 10)
      - 2001-2002 (Box 10)
      - 2002-2003 (Box 10)
      - 2003-2006 (Box 10)
    - Individual Events-Middle Level 1998-2001
      - 1998-1999 (Box 10)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 10)
      - 2000-2001 (Box 10)
      - various years (Box 10)
  - Mailings
    - Bound Materials 1968-1969 (Box 11)
    - Bound Materials (Forensics) 1969-1970 (Box 11)
    - Bound Materials (Debate, J.S. Knight) 1969-1970 (Box 11)
    - Bound Materials (Student Congress, One-Act Plays) 1969-1970 (Box 11)
    - Bound Materials (Forensics) 1970-1971 (Box 11)
    - Bound Materials (J.S. Knight, Discussion, Forensic Council) 1970-1971 (Box 11)
    - Bound Materials (Discussion) 1970-1971 (Box 11)
    - Bound Materials (One-Act Plays) 1970-1971 (Box 11)
    - Bound Materials (Miscellaneous) 1970-1971 (Box 11)
    - Bound Materials (Forensics) 1971-1972 (Box 11)